中国是世界上最神秘的国度之一
China is one of the most fascinating countries in the world,
历史，传统与日新月异的科技在此交融碰撞
a place where history, tradition, and rapid innovation collide.
这里既是人类最古老文明的摇篮
This place is home to some of humanity's oldest civilizations,
同时也坐落着宛如未来之城的都市
and at the same time, to cities that look like they were built for the future.
然而，正如中国的现实世界广袤而独特
But just as China's physical world is vast and unique,
其数字空间亦是如此
so is its digital world, too.
与大多数国家不同
Unlike most countries,
中国的互联网并非运行于我们所熟知的全球平台之上
China's internet doesn't run on the same global platform as many of us are used to.
它拥有自成一派的系统，服务器，乃至应用程序
Instead, it has its own system, its own servers, and even its own apps.
微信取代了WhatsApp
WeChat instead of WhatsApp,
微博取代了Twitter
Weibo instead of Twitter,
而抖音则取代了TikTok
and Douyin instead of TikTok.
其实是一家的
数十亿用户每日连接于此
Billions of users connected every day
构成一个几乎与西方世界完全割裂的线上生态圈
on an online ecosystem that exists almost entirely apart from the West.
这种隔绝造就了某些非凡之物
This separation has created something remarkable.
一个让潮流，社群，乃至都市传说都以一种外界罕见的方式演进的空间
A space where trends, communities, and even myths evolve in ways the rest of the world rarely sees.
而在那些流转于中国各大论坛，社交媒体，以及早期互联网低语中的无数故事里
And within those countless stories that circulate across Chinese forums, social media, and whispers on the early internet,
有些因其绮丽，悲怆与可怖而脱颖而出
some stand out from their beauty, their tragedy, and their horror.
其中一个流传最久远的故事始于二十世纪九十年代中期
One of the most enduring stories begins in the mid-1990s,
在北京的顶尖学府，清华大学
at Beijing's prestigious Tsinghua University.
故事围绕着一位才华横溢的年轻学子
It starts with a gifted young student,
一场突如其来的神秘疾病
a sudden, mysterious illness,
以及一次为挽救她而做出的绝望尝试
and a desperate attempt to save her
这次尝试后来成为了中国互联网最早的伟大谜案之一
that would make history as one of the first great mysteries of the Chinese internet.
当大多数人想到九十年代的中国时
When most people think of China in the 1990s,
他们脑海中浮现的是一个向世界敞开大门的国家
they picture a country opening its doors to the world.
摩天大楼在北京和上海拔地而起
Skyscrapers, rising in Beijing and Shanghai.
但在这场变革的浪潮之下
But behind that transformation,
互联网才刚刚崭露头角
the internet was only just beginning to take shape.
大学的主干网络，研究服务器
University backbones, research servers,
以及连接中国与世界的第一批谨慎链路
and the first cautious connections linking China to the rest of the world.
而正是在这个脆弱的早期网络上
And it was through this fragile early network
这个国家最黑暗的谜团之一即将揭晓
that one of the country's darkest mysteries would unfold.
故事始于北京的清华大学
We started at Tsinghua University in Beijing,
一个素有“中国麻省理工”之称的地方
often called China's MIT.
一位名叫朱令的二十一岁学生是这一切的中心
A 21-year-old student named Zhu Ling was at the center of it all,
她在化学领域才华出众，亦在音乐上天赋异禀
brilliant in chemistry, gifted in music.
朋友们记得她弹奏着古老的古琴
Friends remembered her playing the ancient Guqin,
在北京音乐厅的灯光下演出
performing pieces under the lights of the Beijing concert hall.
但在1994年底，她的生命轨迹却开始分崩离析
But in late 1994, her life began to unravel.
起初只是些微不足道的症状，胃痛和疲惫
At first it was small things, stomach pain, and exhaustion.
然后，她开始脱发
And then the hair loss started.
几周之内，她那头乌黑亮丽的长发已然脱落殆尽
Within weeks, her long black hair was gone.
医生们辗转于各大医院
Doctors cycled through hospitals,
试图寻找一个合理的解释，自身免疫性疾病，病毒感染
searching for explanation, autoimmune diseases, viral infections.
但无一吻合
But nothing fit.
到了1995年春天，朱令逐渐陷入瘫痪
By the spring of 1995, Zhu Ling was slipping into paralysis.
她的身体一寸寸地失控
Her body falling piece by piece.
直至陷入昏迷
Until she fell into a coma.
她的同学们心急如焚
Her classmates were desperate.
在一个没有谷歌，没有Reddit的时代
In an era before Google, before Reddit,
他们做了一件当时几乎无法想象的事情
they did something almost unthinkable for the time.
他们将她的故事发布到了互联网上
They took her story to the internet.
1995年4月10日，学生们在Usenet
On April 10, 1995, students posted an SOS to Usenet,
一个早期的在线论坛上，用英文详述了朱令的怪异症状，发布了一封求救信
one of the earliest online forums detailing Zhu Ling's strength symptoms in English.
他们恳求任何可能识别这种病症的人伸出援手
They begged for help from anyone who might recognize the pattern.
接下来发生的事情如今已成为传奇
And what happened next is now legendary.
回复如潮水般从世界各地涌来
Replies came pouring in from across the world.
那些素未谋面的医生和专家们，却都洞察到了同一个危险信号
Doctors and specialists who have never even met her, but saw the same red flag.
铊中毒
Thallium poisoning.
一种罕见而致命的重金属
A rare and deadly heavy metal.
症状分毫不差
The exact symptoms matched.
神经损伤，腹部剧痛
Nerve damage, abdominal pain, a
乃至她指甲上的苍白纹路
nd even the pale lines on her fingernails.
全世界的智慧诊断出了一个中国顶尖医院都束手无策的病例
The world had diagnosed a case that China's top hospitals had missed.
协和医院早先“排除铊中毒”可能性，事后拒绝承认朱令为铊中毒
详情参阅百度百科“朱令事件”或维基百科“朱令铊中毒事件”
到了五月，北京的医生们终于为她进行了检测
And by May, doctors in Beijing finally tested her.
引用自维基百科：
由于互联网上的回信怀疑是铊中毒，当朱令父母得知
北京市劳动卫生职业病防治研究所的陈震阳教授可做铊中毒鉴定后
在一位协和医生的暗中帮助下，取得朱令的尿液，脑脊液，血液，指甲和头发
于1995年4月28日来到北京市劳动卫生职业病防治研究所进行检验
测定显示，“所有标本中均有很高的含铊量，高于健康人千百倍
从而铊中毒的诊断得到证实。”
结果证实了是铊中毒
Thallium was confirmed.
他们争分夺秒地进口解药
They scrambled to import the antidote.
解药奏效了
And it worked.
但仅仅是堪堪赶上
But only just in time.
1995年8月31日，朱令从昏迷中苏醒
On August 31, 1995, Zhu Ling woke up from her coma.
她活了下来，但伤害已不可逆转
She had survived, but the damage was permanent.
她的视力，记忆和行动能力都已支离破碎
Her vision, memory, and movement were all shattered.
从此，她的父母成为了她的照料者
From then on, her parents became her caretakers,
背负着她本该拥有的璀璨人生的重量
carrying the weight of life she could have lived.
但故事并未就此结束
But that wasn't the end of the story.
它只是另一个谜团的开端
It was only the beginning of another mystery.
究竟是谁对她下的毒手？
Who poisoned her?
嫌疑最终落在了她的一位室友身上
Suspicion landed on a roommate.
她是为数不多能在实验室接触到铊的人之一
One of the few with axes of thallium in a lab.
她接受了讯问，但从未被起诉
She was questioned, but never charged.
多年来，有关方面的沉默只让揣测的火焰愈烧愈旺
And over the years, the silence of authorities only fueled speculation.
在网上，朱令的名字成为了一声抗议的呐喊
Online, Zhu Ling's name became a rallying cry protest.
请愿，无休止的辩论，以及那些悬而未决的问题，其意义甚至超越了案件本身
Petitions, endless debates, and unanswered questions became bigger than the case itself.
一个人怎能在大庭广众之下犯下如此罪行而逍遥法外？
How could someone get away with this in plain sight?
几十年后，法医科学提供了一条令人不寒而栗的线索
Decades later, forensic science offered a haunting clue.
研究人员分析了朱令保存下来的几缕头发
Researchers analyzed strands of Zhu Ling saved hair.
他们如同绘制年轮一般
They mapped the thallium concentrations like tree rings,
标绘出头发中的铊浓度，揭示了长达数月的持续性投毒
showing a pattern of repeated poisoning over months,
并在她倒下前有一次剧烈的剂量爆发
followed by a sharp burst right before her collapse.
这是蓄意所为，是有人干的
It was deliberate that someone had done this.
但始终无人为此承担罪责
But still, no one was held responsible.
朱令一直活到了2023年
Zhu Ling lived until 2023.
在北京去世，享年五十岁
She died in Beijing at 50 years old.
在承受了近三十年的苦难之后
After nearly three decades of suffering.
当消息传来，那个曾拯救过她的互联网，再一次为她哀悼
When the news broke, the internet that had once saved her, mourned her again.
不仅是为那被窃取的人生，也为那永未浮出水面的真相
Not just the life that was stolen, but the truth that never surfaced.
时至今日，朱令的故事被铭记为一个转折点
And today, Zhu Ling's story is remembered as a turning point.
借由线上陌生人的集体智慧，得以解决的首例重大医疗案件
The first major medical case solved through the collective knowledge of strangers online.
它证明了互联网能够拯救生命
Proof that the internet could save lives.
同时，也提醒着我们它的局限
At the same time, it's a reminder of its limits.
因为纵然有数百万人齐心协力为她诊断
Because while millions of people came together to diagnose her,
即便是互联网，也未能将正义送达
not even the internet could deliver the justice.
In the late 2010s, as livestream culture exploded across China,
10年代末，直播文化迅速席卷中国
one figure rose higher than almost anyone else.
有一个主播，可以说是“会当凌绝顶”
Literally.
字面意义上的
His name was Wu Yongning.
此人名叫吴永宁
And he called himself a rooftopper.
自称「rooftopper」
*rooftopper没有约定俗成的翻译
意思是拍摄高空极限视频的人
A performer who scaled skyscrapers, cranes, and towers without ropes or safety gear.
主打不用安全绳徒手攀登摩天大楼、塔吊和高塔
Bouncing on edges where a slip meant death.
在高空建筑的边缘上表演各种特技
Wu had grown up poor with dreams of becoming an actor.
吴永宁出身贫寒，梦想是成为演员
He did stunt work in local films, even martial arts shows,
他在当地的影视剧，和武术表演中当过特技演员
but never found steady success.
均未获得成功
What he did find was, was a phone,
但他另辟蹊径，拿起手机
an audience, and a niche.
给爱看跑酷的观众直播
And by 2017,
到2017年
his short videos of death-defying climbs were going viral on platforms like Huo Shan and Weibo.
他拍摄的极限攀爬短视频，在火山和微博等平台上爆火
Thousands tuned in to see him hanging one-handed from a ledge of a 40-story tower.
无数人涌进直播间，只为看他单手悬挂40层高楼的外沿
Or tiptoeing across beams thinner than his own shoes.
或者看他走过比鞋还窄的钢梁
To his fans, he was fearless.
在粉丝眼中，他无所畏惧
And to his critics, he was reckless.
在黑子们眼中，这是没脑子
But behind that persona was pure pressure.
网络世界的光鲜亮丽背后，蕴藏着巨大压力
Livestream platforms in China had turned danger into revenue,
在直播平台眼里，他的特技越危险，收益越高
likes, donations, and contracts
点赞、打赏、合同
tied to stunts he had to outdo the last.
都与他能否超越上一次的极限表演挂钩
Wu was only 26 years old, supporting his family,
那时吴永宁只有26岁，肩负着养家的重担
hoping to marry his girlfriend and promising bigger feats to sponsors.
还要和女友结婚，答应赞助商带来更惊险的表演
The higher he climbed, the more he needed the risk.
他只能往更高、更危险的地方爬
On November 8th, 2017, Wu traveled to Changsha in the Hunan Providence.
2017年11月8日，吴永宁来到湖南长沙
*吴永宁是湖南宁乡人
The Huayuan International Center was one of the tallest buildings in the city.
挑战长沙最高的建筑之一，「华远国际中心」
62 stories of glass and steel.
整整62层的玻璃与钢筋
He carried his phone, set it up to record, and went to work.
他把手机架好、打开录像，开始表演
The footage, later confirmed by authorities,
录像经警方证实为真
showed him attempting his most dangerous stunt yet.
记录了他最危险的一次挑战
Pulling himself up from the outer ledge of the tower, dangling over 200 meters in the air.
在200米高楼的外沿做引体向上
He raised himself once, twice,
一次、两次
and on the third try, his arm trembled.
第三次，手臂开始颤抖
His grip started to slip.
他的手已经抓不紧了
He clawed to the edge for 4 or 5 seconds,
就这样拼命硬撑了4、5秒
and then... he fell.
然后...掉了下去
Wu Yongning's phone captured it all.
吴永宁的手机记录下了全部过程
And when the news broke weeks later, reactions were conflicted.
几周后消息传出，舆论相当两极化
Fans mourned. Others scolded him for recording death.
粉丝为他哀悼，也有人指责他拿死亡当表演
His girlfriend revealed he had been hoping to win enough in sponsorships to propose marriage.
后来吴永宁的女友透露，他是想拿够赞助商的钱娶她结婚
Officials condemned rooftopping as illegal, life-threatening behavior.
上面谴责这种极限攀爬行为违法，且极度危险
And platforms tightened restrictions on livestream stunts.
各大平台也开始收紧直播特技的规定
But the legacy lingered.
但他的影响仍未消散
Wu Yongning became both a martyr and a warning.
吴咏宁成了一个殉道者，一个警示
China's first and most famous rooftoper.
中国第一位、也是最著名的rooftoper
He turned skyscrapers into a stage, till the stage claimed him.
摩天大楼就是他的舞台，却因舞台而亡
In January 2022, a short video surfaced on Douyin, the Chinese version of TikTok.
2022年1月，抖音上出现了一个短视频
The footage came from Feng County, in Jiangsu, Providence.
视频拍摄于江苏徐州的丰县
And it immediately went viral.
瞬间引爆网络
The clip is simple.
内容很简短
A man walks into a small shed with a pot of food.
男子端着一锅食物，走进简陋的小屋
Sitting inside is a woman, chained by her neck.
屋子里坐着一个女人，脖子上拴着铁链
She looks thin, disoriented, and confused.
女人身体瘦削、神情恍惚，目光涣散
Next to her, on the floor, are basic bedding and housing items.
地上铺着简陋的被褥和生活用品
Very quickly, it was discovered that this woman was the mother of eight children.
很快，人们就发现女人竟然生了8个孩子
The video spread across Douyin, Waibo, and Bilibili at lightning speed.
视频在抖音、微博、B站等平台上直接爆了
Generating outrage.
激起网民众怒
Millions of comments began asking, why is she chained?
无数评论质问道“为什么要把她锁起来？”
And how is she the mother of so many children?
“为什么她会生这么多孩子？”
Authorities in Feng County first claimed that the woman suffered from mental illness.
丰县当地政府的说法是，该女子患有精神疾病
And was being cared for by her husband, a local farmer named Dong Zhimin.
她的丈夫董志民在当地务农，一直照顾着她
But those answers only created more questions.
质疑之声接踵而至
If she was mentally ill, why was she raising eight children?
如果她精神失常，怎么可能养8个孩子？
And why is she chained up in a freezing shed
为什么要把她锁在寒冷的棚屋里
instead of treated at a hospital?
而不是送去医院？
Within days, internet users uncovered further details.
没多长时间，网友便挖出了更多细节
Her name was Xiaohuamei.
女子名叫小花梅
And many began to suspect that she was a victim of human trafficking.
很多人怀疑她是董志民买来的
Independent volunteers traveled to Feng County,
有一些人自发前往丰县
filming the shed and confirming the chain.
拍下了棚屋，证实脖子上的铁链是真的
Their videos were quickly deleted as they were posted.
视频刚发出来就被光速下架
But the mirrors never stopped.
但是补档绝不缺席
The pressure grew so large that officials had to release new statements.
舆论压力越来越大，当地政府不得不多次发布新通告
Each one contradicting the last.
里面的说法自相矛盾
First, they denied the trafficking.
一开始说她不是拐卖来的
Then they admitted issues brought from another Providence under unclear circumstances.
然后又说她是外省拐到这儿的，具体情况不明
And finally, after weeks of backlash,
数周后，在舆论持续发酵下
they admitted that multiple people were involved in moving her illegally across providences.
ZF才承认，这起跨省拐卖案牵涉到多人
And that her documentation had been falsified.
她的身份证和户口也是假的
Several local officers were later punished for negligence.
随后几名政府官员因工作不当被处分
But despite the reports, not all details were ever clarified.
即便如此，还是有很多不为人知的细节
Who exactly sold her?
人贩子是谁？
实际上调查出来了，是时立忠、桑合妞等人
How long has she been chained?
小花梅被关了多久？
And why did it take a viral video for intervention to happen?
为什么要等到视频火了才有人管？
Many of these questions remained unanswered.
这些问题都没有答案
The viral Douyin video forced nationwide attention.
那段抖音视频引起全国关注
It sparked conversations on women's rights,
它引发了关于女性权利
human trafficking, and rural poverty in China.
人口拐卖，以及中国农村贫困问题的讨论
Hashtags were censored, posts were deleted, and yet the story spread further.
ban掉相关话题、贴子后，反而越传越广
Even international media outlets like the BBC and the New York Times picked it up.
连BBC和《纽约时报》等海外媒体都开始报道
Implifying the clip outside of China.
让这段视频传到了国外
The image of a woman chained by her neck,
脖子上套着铁链的女人
staring blankly at the camera, became a symbol.
呆滞地看向镜头，成了一种象征
For many, it was proof of hidden suffering in rural China.
对许多人来说，那就是中国农村不为人知的苦难
For others, it showed the power of a single short video
还证明了短视频的力量
to break through censorship and expose a hidden crime.
突破审查限制，让罪行重见天日
And even now, years later, the original clip is extremely hard to find.
多年过去，原版视频已经很难找到了
But the outrage never fully disappeared.
但是愤怒 从未消散
The chain woman in Fang County remains one of the darkest
丰县“铁链女”事件，依然是中国互联网历史上最黑暗
and most disturbing viral videos in Chinese internet history.
最令人不安的现象级视频之一
In the vast landscape of Chinese internet oddities,
在中国互联网广阔的离奇事件中
some entries are so bizarre they feel almost like urban legends.
有些离奇得像都市传说
One of these is simply titled, The Man and His Telephone.
其中一个是《人与电话》
And at first glance, that sounds mundane, almost boring.
光看名字倒是没啥
The clip it refers to is anything but that.
视频内容可不是
It isn't a surveillance footage or it's not found film.
这并非监控录像或「已找回媒体」
It's actually a skit performed by Chen Peisi, one of the most famous comedians in China.
而是中国著名喜剧演员陈佩斯表演的小品
Throughout the 1980s and 1990s,
在上世纪八九十年代
Chen was a household name,
陈佩斯可以说是家喻户晓
loved for his sharp wit and slapstick performances.
以犀利的幽默和夸张的肢体喜剧深受喜爱
Which is exactly what made this particular video so unsettling.
正因如此，才显得短片如此诡异
The premise is simple, a man sitting with his telephone.
故事很简单，就陈佩斯坐在电话面前
But as the minutes pass, it begins to unravel.
然后，诡异的事情越来越多
The ringing of the phone drives him into madness.
电话不停的响，快把陈佩斯听疯了
Slowly, until the comedy vanishes.
然后短片就跟喜剧没什么关系了
And what should have been in just another sketch,
一个普通的小品
takes on a surreal, almost nightmarish quality.
朝着超现实、灵异的方向展开
Viewers have described it as feeling like analog horror wrapped in everyday reality.
观众形容，它更像是披着日常外壳的「模拟恐怖」
A familiar figure, a familiar object, suddenly soared into something uncanny.
日常生活中再常见不过的人和物，忽然变得诡异陌生
And what makes this even stranger is its scarcity.
更奇怪的是，这段视频极为罕见
Despite Chen's immense fame, this performance is rarely aired.
虽然陈佩斯很有名，但《人与电话》几乎没有重播过
It's even harder to find online.
在网上更稀有
And for decades, it slipped under the radar,
几十年来，这部短片悄无声息
till fragments started resurfacing on Chinese forums.
最近几年才零零散散的出现在中国的论坛里
Some interpret it as satire of modern life.
有些人认为短片讽刺了现代生活
Or a metaphor for technology's suffocating presence.
还有人说这是隐喻现代科技无孔不入，令人窒息
Others swear that there's something darker at play.
甚至有人相信背后藏着更黑暗的秘密
Why else would a clip featuring one of China's most beloved comedians be so difficult to track down?
不然，为什么陈佩斯这种大腕演的短片会如此难找？
Why would it appear, then disappear,
为什么它总是出现又消失
as if someone wanted it to be buried?
像是被刻意隐藏起来？
And whether intentional or not, the effect is chilling.
无论这是不是刻意为之，效果都令人毛骨悚然
It blurs the line between comedy, psychological breakdown,
它模糊了喜剧与心理崩溃之间的界线
between performance and possession,
也模糊了表演与失控之间的界线
a man alone with his telephone
一个孤独的男人，对着电话
unraveling in front of an audience.
在观众面前走向崩溃
2022年末，在吉林省
In late 2022, Jilin Providence
一名少女在凌晨时分
a teenage girl was caught on a CCTV
被监控拍到正走在一座桥上
walking across a bridge in early morning hours.
接着，她就凭空消失了
And then, she simply just vanished.
没有留下一丝一毫的踪迹
No exit and no trace.
女孩名叫郑春梅，年仅十八岁
The girl's name was Zheng Chunmei, only 18 years old.
监控录像记录的内容非常简单
The video is very simple.
本段监控录像为吉林市另一起失踪案件，应为原作者查找资料时的失误
凌晨四点刚过，女孩进入了画面，径直走过桥梁
She enters the frame walking alone across a bridge, just after 4 a.m.
桥面空空如也，街道一片寂静
The bridge is empty the streets are quiet
而她却再也没有走出摄像头的视野
and then she never leaves the camera's view.
她没有从马路对面向前走出来
She doesn't come out on the other side of the road.
她也没有掉头
She doesn't turn back
她就这么消失了
she's just gone.
监控录像引发了大规模的搜寻
The footage sparked massive search
警方救援队和志愿者把河道和周围的街道翻了个底朝天
police rescue teams and volunteers comb the river in the surrounding streets.
他们检查了过往车辆
They checked passing vehicles
并逐帧观察了周围区域的录像
they reviewed every frame of the footage around the area.
但无论调查团搜寻得有多仔细
But no matter how closely they looked
都始终得不出一个明确的答案
there was no clear answer.
有人认为她跳进了河里
Some believe she jumped into the river
但尸体却一直没有被发现
there no body was ever recovered.
另有人提出了谋杀的可能性
Other suspected foul play
说或许是有人在摄像头盲区里截住了她
that someone may have intercepted her off camera.
然而谜题却没能得到解释
But the mystery remained
另一台理应记录下事情全过程的摄像头
one camera that should have explained what happened
却没有展露出丝毫异常
instead showed nothing at all.
在网上，阴谋论迅速传播开来
Online theories spread fast
有人认为录像被动了手脚
some argue the footage have been tampered with
部分帧被剪辑过，或者被模糊处理了
that certain frames are cut or blurred out.
还有人提出了更超自然的解释
Others pushed more supernatural explanations
说她可能是走去了另一个维度
that she'd walked into another dimension
或者说，河流以超乎人类认知的方式吞噬了她
or that the river claimed her in ways beyond human explanation.
由于案件一直没能彻底被侦破
Because the case was never fully solved
阴谋论的声量变得越来越大
these theories only grew louder.
说起互联网恐怖
When you think of Internet horror
最具标志性的莫过于“后室”了
one of the most iconic modern myths is the back rooms.
它于2019年左右在西方互联网兴起
It started in the West around 2019
起初只是一条简简单单的蠕动意面帖子
with a simple creepy pasta post.
照片中是一个无边无际的黄色办公空间
A photo of an endless yellow office space
潮湿的地毯，嗡嗡作响的日光灯
damped carpets, buzzing fluorescent lights
若你脱离你所处的现实
and promised that if you know clip out of reality
就有可能被困在里面
you might find yourself trapped there.
仅凭这一张图片
And from that one image
“后室”便一举发展成了一整个互联网共创怪谈体系
the back rooms exploded into an entire Internet mythology.
人们基于它创作了游戏、短片，乃至整个恐怖宇宙
People built games, short films, and entire universes of horror.
所有这些都围绕着同一个核心理念：
All centered on the same idea
迷失在熟悉却又不对劲、无边无尽的阈限空间之中
being lost in endless, liminal space, that feels familiar but wrong.
但在中国，大家对这种理念的演绎更为独特
But China has its own spin on the concept.
在中国最大的同性交友网站比比汗丽丽上
On Bilibili,
创作者们开始尝试被称为“中国后室”的本土化创作
creaters begin experimenting with the known as the Chinese back rooms.
乍一看，两种后室非常相似：
At first glance, they look very similar
长长的走廊、闪烁的灯光
long hallways, flickering lights
以及那种“你不该出现在此地”的感觉
and the feeling that you're somewhere you shouldn't be.
但其细节却具有鲜明的中国风格
But the details are distinctly Chinese.
没有了泛黄的壁纸和格子间
Instead of the yellowish wallpaper and the cubicles
“中国后室”以废弃医院、昏暗的学校走廊
the Chinese back rooms feature abandoned hospitals, darkened school corridors,
以及上世纪90年代老旧的政府建筑为主要场景
and outdated government buildings from the 1990s.
这些地方几乎是每个中国人
Their places almost everyone in China
在人生某个阶段都会遇到的
have encountered at some point in their life.
荒废的童年教室
A child's classroom left behind
一间似乎永远都不会变样的医院候诊室
a hospital waiting room that never seems to change.
还有一个摆满了无穷无尽的灰色文件柜的政府办公室
And a government office with endless grey filing cabinets.
一些创作者发掘的更深入一些
Some creators have gone further
将这种风格与“鬼工厂”的概念融合
by blending this style with a ghost factory.
这种美学以巨大的工厂为主要元素
This aesthetic takes the king factories
将其呈现为无边无际的阈限空间
and presents them as endless liminal spaces.
对我而言，这正是中国后室如此迷人的关键之所在
And to me, that's what makes the Chinese back rooms so fascinating.
它们表明，一个简单的概念
They show a single idea
也就是“对无尽的阈限空间的恐惧”
the fear of an endless liminal space
会根据文化背景而演变
can evolve depending on culture
在西方，是办公空间
in the west, its office spaces
而在中国，则是代表着日常生活的场所：
and China is the institutions that define daily life
医院、学校和工厂
hospitals, schools, and factories.
它们使人感到不寒而栗的方式各不相同
Both are very unsettling in their own way.
说实话，这正是这种本土化改编的绝妙之处
And honestly, that's what makes this adaptation so cool.
它不仅仅是对西方互联网怪谈的简单复制
It's not just a copy of Western Internet myth
而是一种深刻的重新诠释
it's a reinterpretation.
它证明了“阈限恐怖”具有普遍性
The one that proves liminal horror is universal
与此同时又深深植根于本土特色
but also deeply local.
说到互联网上的恐怖内容
When we think of horror on the Internet
大部分人首先会想到油管
most of us turn to YouTube,
像是《Local 58》或《曼德拉记录》这样的模拟恐怖系列
in a like horror series like Local 58 or the Mandela catalog,
围绕着低保真的广播、诡异的信号和噩梦般的插播内容
and our built entire communities around low five broadcast
形成了完整的社区文化
crept as signals, and nightmares interruptions.
但咱中国人有自己的油管，噼里啪啦
But China has its own version of YouTube, BiliBili.
尽管平台不同
And although the platform is different
内容却有诸多相似之处
the content often feels familiar.
它有自己的烂梗、自己的网络文化
It has its own memes, its own internet culture
以及自己的互联网恐怖
and its own horror.
Bilibili 上最奇特的恐怖风格之一被称为“模拟恐怖”
One of the strangest sub-genres on BiliBili is called Simulated Horror.
它与我们西方人所说的“拟态恐怖”非常相似
And it's very similar to analog horror we have in the west.
“模拟恐怖”的核心主要有两个概念：
At the core of the Simulated Horror are two main ideas
视觉劫持和电视插播
eye jackings and TV interruption.
某些视频会有意模仿紧急广播
You'll see clips styled like emergency broadcast
冷静的声线突然开始播报令人毛骨悚然的东西
where a calm boy suddenly announces something terrifying,
也许是关于某种怪物的警告
maybe a creature warning
也许是预警一种根本不存在的灾难
maybe a disaster that doesn't actually exist.
另一种视频则模仿了失踪人口警报
Another video is mimic missing person alerts
在插播时段，一个孩子的脸会闪过屏幕
though setting interruptions, where a child's face flashes on screen.
但不同的是，这里的警报会出现故障、失真
Except here, the alerts glitch, distort
或传达毫无逻辑的信息
or deliver information that makes in those sense.
之所以能吓到人，就是因为它让人感觉很真实
It's a fear that works because it feels real.
这些广播被设计得看起来非常拟真
The broadcaster designed to look authentic
足以让人误以为它们是
just believable enough that you can mistake them for something
政府真的播出过的内容
the government really aired.
西方的拟态恐怖往往倾向于怀旧：
Western interlock horror often leans on nostalgia
VHS画面、本地接入频道、充满年代感的图像
VHS screen, local access channels, aesthetic-filled screens.
它之所以可怕，是因为它看起来像过去的遗物
It's scary because it looks like a relic of the past
一件从90年代或80年代挖掘出来的，受损的“文物”
a corrupted artifact, pulled from the 90s or 80s.
Bilibili 的“模拟恐怖”则让人感觉有所不同
BiliBili's Simulated Horror feels different.
这些视频反映了生活在高度互联、被监控社会中的现实
These videos reflect the reality of living in a hyper-connected monitor society
在这样的社会里，一次广播插播会让人感觉具有权威性
where a broadcast interruption feels authoritative
甚至事关生死
or even life or death.
最能代表模拟恐怖的作品之一
One of the best examples of the sub-genre
莫过于《雾潮来袭》（BV1pm4y1H7QL）
is a clip called Fog Tide Incoming.
视频开头就像真实的紧急播报一样
At first, it looks like a real emergency feed.
公共安全广播警告居民，浓雾正席卷这座城市
The public safety broadcast warning residents that a heavy fog is rolling into the city
并附带了分步的疏散指南
accompanied by a step-by-step evacuation guidelines.
表面上看
And on the surface
它感觉和我们之前谈到的失踪人口插播
it feels just as authentic as missing person interruptions
或被劫持的警报一样真实可信
or hijacked alerts we talked about earlier.
但两者还是存在区别的
But there's a difference.
那些逼真的插播
There's realistic interruptions
屏幕上闪过的失踪儿童啦，直播频道突发的劫持啦
missing children's flashing on screen, sudden hijack needs of a live channel
之所以令人恐惧，正是因为它们有可能发生
or terrifyingly precisely because they could happen
它们植根于现实之中
they're grounded in reality.
而《雾潮来袭》则更偏向虚构
Fog Tide Incoming, on the other hand, leads more into fiction.
广播给出的指南毫无逻辑
The guidelines make no sense
仿佛指南的目的不是为了保护，而是为了伤害
as if they were designed to harm rather than protect.
然后，在播报的中途
And then, in the middle of the broadcast
一个微笑的花朵头赫然出现
a smiling flower head appears.
这是任何真实的紧急播报中绝不会出现的内容
Something no real emergency feed would ever include.
同样让观众恐惧，但是以一种截然不同的方式
It's unsettling but in a different way.
它不再让人感觉像是井然有序的现实世界正在崩溃
Instead of it feeling like a real-world system breaking down
而更像是踏入了另一个完全不同的现实
it feels like stepping into another reality altogether
在那里，广播本身成为了恐怖的征兆
where the broadcast themselves become indices of horror.
看到两种不同的文化和两个不同的平台
It's very interesting to see two different cultures
衍生出同一个可怕的概念
and two different platforms
还挺有意思的
but the same terrifying concept.